The ship left the port of Oslo at 21:45 local time - 2 hours and a quarter delayed.
The journey would have started already at 19:30, but work on boarding passenger cars and trucks took longer than expected.
The journey to Fredrikshamn goes painlessly at first until it was between 01: 45-02: 00 on the night of April 7.
The ship was now out on open water in a part of the North Sea called Skagerack and most of the passengers were sleeping.
On deck 4, some passengers are suddenly awakened from their sleep when they hear a crackling sound out in the corridor.
A few doors away is a pile of bedding on the floor that burns.
Fortunately, they manage to extinguish the fire together with the crew.
One of the crew members went up to the command bridge and announced the first mate who at that time had the guard.
He in turn went and announced to the captain of what had happened and told the captain that "someone is playing Pyroman".
After captain Hugo Larsen was announced, the first mate was sent down to the fire site to check.
It was made sure to be properly extinguished and cleaned up.
After that, the first mate called the captain on the bridge again and announced that everything was under control.
But it all didn't end there.
Sometime just after 02:00, one more fire arose on deck 3 outside a cabin in a corridor on the starboard side.
This was near the stairs leading up to tires 4 and 5. Within a few minutes, the fire had spread so much that the entire corridor was in flames
And thick smoke looked up the stairwell and began to fill the corridors on tires 4 and 5.
There were alarms from a number of different fire alarms in the corridors on decks 4 and 5 when the passengers there had discovered the fire.
When the captain learned about this it was around 02:15 and when the first mate entered the bridge he received orders from the captain to send out the signal "fire alarm" all over the ship.
The captain triggered the self -closure of the fire doors in the areas where the fire alarm buttons had been pressed by the passengers.
But since no button had been pressed in where the fire started on the starboard side by deck 3, the fire doors were left open there.
The walls and ceiling on deck 3 were covered with plastic laminate and when it burned there it created a smoke that contained high levels of hydrogen cyanide and carbon monoxide
And after only 10 minutes, the corridors had reached a deadly concentration of the two gases.
At 02:24 they now turned off the ship's propulsion and then started the fire pumps but the fire was already out of control.
Captain Hugo Larsen sent out an emergency signal to Tjøme Radio in Norway, announcing the fire on board and that the passengers and crew would now start moving towards the lifeboats.
On board, there is currently total panic among passengers.
Many are struggling through the smoke -filled corridors.
Some people have already died of the toxic smoke and passengers may step over them in order to reach.
159 people lost their lives that night.
The investigations conducted afterwards by the forensic authorities show they probably died quickly.
It was a combination of a number of causes, partly the fire itself but also of high carbon dioxide content as well as the toxic smoke containing carbon monoxide and hydrogen cyanide.
It is estimated that the passengers who made their way out into the corridors had not been able to get to any exit before collapsing on the floor.
Most of the dead, which were 99 people, remained in their cabins.
About 50 people were found in the corridors and most were in aft on deck 5.
323 people were rescued from Scandinavian Star that night and only about 30 were injured.
Most had mild smoke poisoning or other lighter injuries such as splits and bruises.
Some were taken ashore via helicopter and others were brought with the vessels to Lysekil, Sandefjord, Fredriksstad and Fredrikshamn.
11.55 During the day, Scandinavian Star was towed to Lysekil and is 21:17 in the evening.
The day after April 8 at 16:30, the fire is finally extinguished and the dead can start to be lifted ashore.
Since the majority of passengers were from Norway, the dead bodies were transported in large white cooling cars with police cards to the Forensic Institute in Oslo.
Two questions quickly appear in the head.
Who built the fires and why did everything go ... so wrong?
Sadly, it has not been possible to determine who or who built the fires on the ship.
After the disaster, an official fire investigation was conducted and there it was concluded that the most likely perpetrator was a passenger on board
named Erik Mørk Andersen, 37 years.
He was previously convicted of murder.
However, he himself died in the flames after the second fire so you couldn't be sure it was he.
An interesting investigation from 2006 by two fire engineers at Lund University of Technology concluded that there were not only two fires on board ..
And the same day as the purchase, they assured the ship for $ 24 million.
According to this theory, the company Sea Escape can thus be the cause of the fire and got some of the crew to set fire to the ship and later get the insurance money.
Why did everything go so wrong then?
How could the fire on board get such a disastrous outcome?
According to the Accident Investigation Board's report, this was due to several things.
Partly that when the captain of the command bridge is notified of the fire, the alarm within the ship is incomplete.
No proper attempt at all extinguish the fires was carried out…
It was even so that the fire manager on board did not know that it was his task.
There were seven smoke diver equipment on board, but no one was used to extinguish the fire or to save any passengers.
3 of them were used in the evacuation of the ship.